October 1, 1946, Nuremberg, Germany. After more than 10 months of trial, 21 defendants between
which include the most important political, military and economic leaders of the
Nazi Germany, listen to the reading of their sentences. These high representatives of the
The criminal National Socialist regime must finally assume responsibility.
for their crimes. Thus, they answer before an international military tribunal that will punish them for the
unspeakable atrocities committed during the Second World War. It is only the first of the
many war crimes trials held after the war and will become
a warning to war criminals and dictators around the world.
Once the true extent of German atrocities was revealed, especially against the
Jews, 12 of the 21 defendants are sentenced to death by hanging. One of them is a former
head of the General Government of Nazi-occupied Poland who, from his position,
was responsible for the exploitation and murder of hundreds of thousands of Polish civilians,
as well as the deportation and murder of Jews. His name is Hans Frank.
Hans Michael Frank, the second of three brothers,
was born on May 23, 1900 in Karlsruhe, then part of the German Empire. His father
Karl was a successful lawyer and his mother Magdalena was the daughter of a prosperous banker.
In 1910, when Hans Frank was 10 years old, his mother abandoned the family for a lover in Prague.
The First World War began on July 28, 1914. Hans, who grew up in Munich, where he also
He graduated from Maximilian High School and enlisted in the German army at the age of seventeen.
but he never served on the front. After the Great War, which ended on 11
November 1918, and during the German Revolution of 1918 to 1919,
Hans Frank served in the Freikorps or independent paramilitary units, participating in the
repression of the Bavarian Soviet Republic, a short-lived unrecognized socialist state in
said area during the German Revolution. Composed mainly of veterans of the
World War I returning from the war, the Freikorps fought
against the communists and other groups he held responsible for the German defeat.
During this time, Frank was also a member of the Thule Society,
a German occult group founded in Munich shortly after World War I,
which took its name from a mythical northern country belonging to legends
Greeks. This society is best known for being the organization that sponsored the Party
German Worker, which Frank, like other members of the Thule Society, joined in 1919.
The German Workers' Party, dissolved in February 1920, was the precursor to the Nazi Party,
officially known as the National Socialist German Workers' Party.
However, Frank waited until September 1923 to become a member of the Sturmabteilung
-the SA-, which was the Nazi paramilitary force also known as the Storm Troopers or
the "Brown Shirts" because of the color of their uniform. One of the first organized activities of the
SA was the Munich Beer Hall Putsch, which took place on 8 and 9 November 1923,
when Adolf Hitler and the Nazi Party led a coalition group in an attempt to overthrow
to the German government. The conspirators hoped to march on Berlin to launch a revolution
throughout the nation, but the uprising failed miserably. Munich police units
They faced the Nazi stormtroopers on their march towards the city center. The two
groups exchanged gunfire, resulting in the deaths of 16 Nazi Party members and
four police officers. This attempted coup d'état became known as the Beer Hall Putsch.
Its leaders, including Adolf Hitler, were arrested. Hitler was found guilty of high
treason and sentenced to five years in prison. However, he only served eight months of his sentence.
After the attempted coup, Frank fled to Italy, where he learned the language, and never returned.
Munich until 1924, after pending legal proceedings were suspended.
On April 2, 1925, Hans Frank married Brigitte Herbst, who was then 29 years old.
She was a stenographer in the Bavarian Parliament and later a secretary at the University of Munich. Brigitte,
who had often told her friends that she had to get married before she turned 30, grew up in
a modest situation and from a very young age aspired to a higher standard of living. In Hans Frank, a
Bavarian 5 years younger, fun-loving, from a wealthy family of lawyers and who
had just obtained his doctorate in Law, he found someone who could fulfill his ambitions.
The marriage was not very cordial, as Frank could not impose himself on his domineering wife and,
Although Brigitte did not have maternal feelings nor did she particularly like children, she became
Hans Frank is the father of five children: two girls and three boys, including Niklas Frank, born
between 1927 and 1939. Brigitte used her children to control her husband so
Whenever she needed him to do something, she would simply say, "Hans, I have borne you five children."
During our interview, Niklas Frank told us that his mother Brigitte had
got his driver's license in Adolf Hitler's car,
but she didn't like the Nazi leader because, according to her, he had "stinky breath."
In 1929 Hitler appointed Hans Frank, who became his personal legal advisor,
head of the Nazi Party's legal department. As the Nazis rose to power,
Frank also acted as the party's lawyer, representing it in over 2,400 cases.
This sometimes led to conflicts with other lawyers. On one occasion,
A former professor addressed him saying:
"I beg you to stay away from these people! Nothing good will come out of there. The movements
"Politicians who start in criminal courts will end up in criminal courts."
One of the factors that helped the Nazis rise to power was propaganda. The Nazis
They used this tool in the late 1920s and early 1930s to enhance
Hitler's image. As a result of this and other aspects, he became extremely popular.
The Nazi Party's meteoric rise to power began in 1930, when it won 107 seats in
the German Parliament, the Reichstag. One of the members of the parliament was Hans Frank.
Adolf Hitler and the Nazi Party came to power in January 1933. In April of that same year,
Frank was appointed Minister of Justice of Bavaria, a position he held until December 1934,
when he became Minister without Portfolio in the Reich government. On June 2,
In 1933 he was appointed Reichsleiter in charge of Legal Affairs, the second political rank.
highest ranking member of the Nazi Party. On June 26, 1933, Frank founded the Academy of Law
German. At its inaugural meeting on October 2, 1933, he was appointed its director.
and in August 1934 he became its president. The Academy was responsible for promoting reform
of German legal life working as a liaison with legislative bodies
to implement the National Socialist program in the fields of law and economics.
Hans Frank also chaired the Academy's Committee on Philosophy of Law and
He was editor of several of its publications. In January 1934, Frank was appointed one
of the three judges of the Supreme Party Court, an internal tribunal of the Nazi Party
created by Adolf Hitler in 1925 to resolve problems and disputes within the organization.
Hans Frank opposed extrajudicial executions because they weakened the power
of the system, both in the Dachau concentration camp and during the "Night of the Knives"
"long". Frank's opinion on what the judicial process required was as follows:
"The function of the judge is to safeguard the concrete order of the racial community,
eliminate dangerous elements, prosecute all acts harmful to the
community and arbitrate disagreements between members of that community. Nazi ideology,
especially as expressed in the Party program and in the
speeches of our Leader, is the basis for interpreting legal sources."
At a conference on National Socialist legal policy held in Rome in April
In 1936, Frank met Benito Mussolini, with whom he soon established a cordial relationship,
among other things because he was able to speak to him without an interpreter. At the end of September 1936,
Frank traveled back to Rome to bring Mussolini Hitler's invitation to visit
Germany. He became Mussolini's personal advisor during this visit.
On November 9 and 10, 1938,
The Nazi leaders unleashed a series of coordinated violent riots
against Jews throughout Germany and the newly incorporated territories.
The Nazi SA and German civilians not only looted 7,500 businesses,
homes and schools owned by Jews, but also destroyed hundreds of
synagogues. 91 Jews were murdered and the German SS and police sent
nearly 30,000 Jewish men to concentration camps, mainly to Dachau.
Kristallnacht was a turning point in the history of the Third Reich,
as it marked the transition from anti-Semitic rhetoric and legislation to
violent and aggressive measures against the Jews that would culminate in the
Holocaust. Many Jews then realized they had to leave Germany.
However, Brigitte Frank never helped any of them. Before the Nazis
came to power, he used to trade furs with them. When a Jew in a queue to obtain
A visa saw her walking with two friends and asked her: "Do you remember me? I need
a visa for my family," she ignored him, turning away and doing nothing for him.
World War II began on September 1, 1939 with the invasion of Poland.
Poland was then fighting a war on two fronts when it was invaded by the
Soviet Union from the east on September 17. Warsaw officially surrendered to the Germans on
September 28th and a day later, in accordance with the secret protocol of their non-aggression pact,
Germany and the Soviet Union divided the country. They divided Poland into thirds: the western third
was annexed to Germany, the eastern third corresponded to the Soviet Union and the third
half became a semi-independent administrative unit, called the General Government,
of which Hans Frank was appointed Governor General by the Führer. The reason was that Hitler
He knew that Frank would not present any obstacles or difficulties to his plans.
Frank described the policy he intended to implement by stating the following:
"Poland will be treated as a colony,
The Poles will become slaves of the Great German World Empire."
Thus, he was the most important administrator in the region but he did not have the freedom to govern.
as I would like since the racial policies carried out in the General Government were the
responsibility of the SS and the police. Frank was not opposed to these goals,
but he hated others interfering in his domains. When Hans Frank asked Himmler,
the head of the SS, what was he doing there when the SS were building the first
concentration camp, he told him directly and clearly: "It's none of your business!"
Hitler intended the General Government to be used as a "racial dumping ground",
an endless supply of slave labor and a place for
mass extermination of European Jews. This area had a total population of
12 million, of whom 1.5 million were Jews. After the Germans
They attacked the Soviet Union in the summer of 1941, incorporating eastern Galicia
to the General Government, adding between three and four million people to the population.
The Germans treated the Poles of the General Government terribly and
They saw it as a source of cheap labor that they could take advantage of at any opportunity.
All opposition was crushed with the utmost brutality. A reign of terror was established,
backed by summary police courts that ordered actions such as shootings
public gatherings of groups of twenty to two hundred Poles and widespread shootings of hostages.
In 1940, Frank clearly showed the extent of this reign of terror with a
cynical comment to a journalist about von Neurath's poster where he advertised
the execution of Czech students. He blurted out: "Large numbers of prisoners were placed in Prague
Red signs reading, "Seven Czechs had been shot today." So I said to myself:
"If I had to put up a sign for every seven Poles shot, the forests of this country would not
would be sufficient to make all the paper." On the other hand, the economic demands on
General Government far exceeded the needs of the occupation army and did not
were in no way proportional to the country's resources. Food grown in Poland
were sent to Germany on such a scale that the rations of the population of the
Occupied territories were reduced to starvation, and epidemics spread.
The Jews of the General Government were subjected to terribly harsh decrees
and from the beginning the Germans confiscated their property and forced them to carry out
forced labor. From the end of 1939, Jews were confined in ghettos,
where they were totally isolated from the outside world and severely restricted from everything.
In a speech to his staff on November 25, 1939, Hans openly described him as a
joy at finally being able to physically approach the Jewish race. “The more that die, the better,” he argued.
On October 16, 1940, Hans Frank announced the creation of the Warsaw Ghetto,
which became the largest of all the Jewish ghettos in occupied Europe
the Nazis during World War II. The ghetto's population, increased by the
Jews forced to move from nearby cities, was estimated at more than
400,000. The German authorities forced the ghetto residents to live in a
of just over 2 square kilometers, with an average of 7.2 people per room.
Proper hygiene was almost impossible, as many homes did not even have running water.
Extreme overcrowding, minimal rations and unsanitary conditions
caused disease, famine, and the death of thousands of Jews every month. In 1941,
The average daily food ration for Jews in Warsaw was limited to 184 calories,
compared to 2,613 calories for Germans. An official German order
established that “the basic supply of the residential district
Jewish life must be less than the minimum necessary to preserve life,
regardless of the consequences." Thus, hunger in the ghetto was so great
that the dying lay in the streets and small children were seen begging.
Between 1940 and mid-1942, 83,000 Jews died of hunger and disease.
When a resident of the Warsaw ghetto died, their families would leave the body in
the street so that a hearse could pick him up in the morning. This service operated every day.
On December 16, 1941, Hans Frank explained to his senior officials the
plan for the imminent annihilation of the Jews. These were his words:
"In any case, a great Jewish migration will begin. But,
What should we do with the Jews? Do you think they will settle in Ostland,
in villages? In Berlin they told us: 'Why so much trouble? We can't do anything with them, not even in
Ostland nor in the Reichskommissariat. So get rid of them yourselves.' Gentlemen,
I ask you to rid yourselves of any feeling of compassion. We must annihilate
to the Jews wherever we find them and whenever possible." And so they did!
In the spring of 1942, the Germans began deporting Jews from
the ghettos to extermination camps located in the Lublin district. Two years later,
By 1944, all the ghettos in the General Government had been liquidated.
While millions of Poles were dying of hunger or being murdered in the extermination centers and
German concentration camps, the Frank family was accustomed to living a lifestyle
luxurious life with good food, big houses and lots of money. Hans Frank ruled Poland as if
if he were a king. In fact, his wife Brigitte often called herself "Queen of Poland."
From November 1939, Hans Frank resided at Wawel Castle in Krakow,
the ancestral seat of the Polish kings, where he ordered to hang in his office “The
“Lady with an Ermine” by Leonardo da Vinci, one of only three da Vinci oil paintings in all
the world. The General Government was soon mockingly called "Frank-Reich" by the
party comrades. Frank hired drivers, housekeepers, servants,
cooks and looted art treasures belonging to the Catholic Church and the Polish nobility.
He was an artistic person and a music lover, he played the piano and enjoyed the
opera. He also played chess and often associated with artists such as the composer
German Richard Strauss, who even wrote a hymn in praise of Hans Frank.
Frank's private residence, Schloss Kressendorf, which served as a weekend house
his family's weekend, was decorated with furniture stolen from aristocratic palaces
Poles. During our interview, Hans Frank's son, Niklas, recalled how his mother
She discarded all the pretty maids because she feared that her unfaithful husband, Hans, would sleep with her.
with all of them. According to his wife, Frank didn't care much about who he had relations with.
Niklas also said that they had never talked about Jews at home,
but he remembered that near his weekend home there were railways and that all the trains
filled with prisoners deported to Auschwitz passed by Kressendorf Castle.
Niklas also remembered how on some occasions Frank's sister went to the
Krakow-Płaszów concentration camp and told the arriving Jews that they
would help them survive if they gave him diamonds. However, despite everything, he never helped anyone.
Frank's wife, Brigitte, also profited from German crimes.
He drove to the ghettos of Krakow and Warsaw in his convertible Mercedes-Benz
with a driver to purchase jewelry, furs and other valuables.
After Hans Frank, a well-known womanizer, met Lilly Groh in 1942,
his childhood sweetheart, he had the intention of leaving his wife and marrying her. However,
Brigitte Frank did not want to give up her status and even declared:
“I’d rather be a widow than divorced from a Reichsminister!” Brigitte,
self-proclaimed Queen of Poland, she also had many extramarital affairs and suffered
several abortions because, quite simply, she wasn't sure who the father was.
To get rid of Groh, she not only described her husband's mistress
as "Jewish" to Reichsführer SS Heinrich Himmler, but intervened with Hitler,
who told Frank that he could only divorce Brigitte if he resigned from his position. However,
This never happened, although Hans Frank later claimed that he submitted applications
He had renounced Hitler on 14 occasions, but the Führer did not allow him to resign.
However, the truth is that deep down he did not want to give up his power.
However, in 1942, Frank became involved in a dispute with Himmler over the type of
legal system that should have been in force in Germany. It also annoyed Hitler with
a series of speeches at the universities of Berlin, Vienna, Heidelberg and Munich in which
He criticized the police state and advocated for an independent judiciary. For this reason, Hitler banned
Frank spoke outside the General Government and excluded him from all Reich positions. It was
dismissed as Reichsleiter of the Nazi Party and as president of the Academy of German Law.
In January 1944, a train on which Frank was traveling to Lviv derailed after unloading
from an explosive device. Although no one died, around 100 Polish hostages
from Montelupich prison were executed as punishment for the act.
On August 1, 1944, the Warsaw Uprising began when the Home Army
Polish, a non-communist underground resistance army with units stationed throughout the
country occupied by the Germans, rose up against the Bavarian authorities in an effort to liberate
the city. The impetus for the uprising was the appearance of Soviet forces
along the eastern bank of the Vistula River. However, the Red Army did not intervene.
166,000 people lost their lives in the uprising,
including perhaps as many as 17,000 Polish Jews who had fought
with the Polish Home Army or had been discovered hiding.
On October 16, 1944, Hans Frank hosted a dinner at Wawel Castle,
in honor of Oskar Dirlewanger, a pedophile Nazi officer who led his 4,000 butchers,
rapists and looters to action against the Warsaw Uprising. Without a second thought
He committed such atrocious crimes that both the army and SS commanders
demanded the withdrawal of their unit. Frank expressed, with these words, his "gratitude and appreciation for the
exemplary operations carried out by his group during the fighting in Warsaw."
On January 17, 1945, as the Soviet army advanced, Hans Frank fled from Krakow.
with 3 trucks full of artworks, including paintings by Rembrandt, Raphael, Da Vinci and a
fake passport in the name "Fischer". His goal was to leave for Argentina with the help of the
Catholic Church. However, Frank did not leave Germany because he did not believe that after the war
would be tried before a military tribunal. He thought that, in the worst case, he and other Nazis would be
sent to the Netherlands, as was the case with Kaiser Wilhelm II after the First World War
World War II. There, they would enjoy the possessions looted during the war years.
When later asked about the stolen art treasures, he replied: “An accusation that
What touches my private life and affects me deeply is the supposed enrichment with works of art.
of the country entrusted to my care. I didn't collect paintings and didn't find time during the war
to seize art treasures. I made sure that all the works of art in the country entrusted to me
under my charge were duly officially registered." The
The three truckloads of art he fled Krakow with did not fall into this category.
However, on May 4, 1945, Frank was captured by American troops.
in Tegernsee, in southern Bavaria. The troops who arrested him were the ones who
They had liberated Dachau five days earlier and had witnessed firsthand
the atrocities of the Nazi regime. After his capture, he had to
walking among a group of American soldiers. They all beat him.
Frank collapsed under this pressure, unable to survive the thought of even harsher treatment,
and attempted suicide. When that failed, he tried again just 48 hours later,
unsuccessfully cutting his left wrist. He would later say:
“I tried to commit suicide because I sacrificed everything for Hitler. And that man for whom I
We sacrificed everything, he left us alone.” As his son Niklas told us, his father had tried
take his own life because he didn't want to be treated the way he had treated others.
Brigitte Frank also faced difficult times. All her friends had
gone and no one wanted to have anything to do with them. In order to buy food,
had to sell all possessions, including jewelry stolen from murdered Jews and
paintings that were taken from Krakow. What remained was confiscated. However,
She still hoped her husband would be released and even planned to have another child with him.
Instead, Hans Frank was tried at the Nuremberg trials, which were held against
representatives of defeated Nazi Germany. He faced three charges: Conspiracy to commit
crimes against peace, war crimes and crimes against humanity.
At the beginning of his testimony, Frank stated that he had a feeling of "terrible guilt" for
the atrocities committed in the occupied territories. But his defense was largely dedicated
measure to try to demonstrate that he was not actually responsible; that he ordered only the measures
necessary pacification measures; that the excesses were due to police activities that did not
were under his control; and that he did not even know about the activities of the camps
concentration camps. As Niklas Frank confirmed, his parents knew everything about the extermination camps.
During the trial he converted to Roman Catholicism and claimed to have had
a series of religious experiences. In the process, he accused the Allies,
especially the Soviets, of their own atrocities during the war and he and Albert
Speer was the only defendant who showed any degree of remorse for his crimes.
He also said the following: “I myself, speaking from the depths of my heart and having
Having lived through the five months of this trial, I want to say that now that I have gained insight
complete of all the horrible atrocities that have been committed, I am possessed by a
deep sense of guilt. Those of us who are guilty must pay the price.” And so it was in his case.
On October 1, 1946, the International Military Tribunal found Hans Frank guilty of
war crimes and crimes against humanity and sentenced him to death by hanging. According to the
verdict, Frank voluntarily and knowingly participated in the terrible crimes described
in Poland; in the economic exploitation of the country in a way that led to the starvation of
a large number of people; in the deportation to Germany as slave laborers of more than one
million Poles; and in a program that involved the murder of at least three million Jews.
After receiving the death sentence,
Frank said, "Death by hanging... he deserved it and expected it."
Frank was executed by US Army Sergeant John C. Woods,
who had no documented experience as an executioner before the war. It is believed that
He was deliberately bad at his job to make the 10 criminals suffer.
Nazi war that he executed that day, as they all perished in a long and agonizing death.
The Nazis executed by Sergeant Woods fell from the gallows with a fall
insufficient to break their necks, causing death by strangulation
which in some cases lasted several minutes. Furthermore, the trapdoor was too small,
which caused several of the convicts to suffer serious head injuries when they fell.
On October 16, 1946, the day of his execution,
Hans Frank was the fifth of the Nuremberg defendants to ascend the scaffold. He was
the only one of the condemned who entered the chamber with a smile on his face.
Afterwards, he spoke his last words: "I am grateful for the kind of treatment I received during
my captivity and I ask God to accept me with mercy." Then Frank was hanged,
but falling from the gallows without enough strength to break his neck,
Her horrific convulsions lasted 11 long minutes before she died. She was 46 years old.
After that, his body was cremated and the ashes were scattered in the Isar River.
Later, Sergeant Woods not only insisted that he had carried out all the executions
correctly, but stated that he was very proud of his work.
After the war, Brigitte, Hans Franks's wife, never said anything again.
positive about the Third Reich. He died on March 9, 1959, on his twentieth birthday
son Niklas. The Frank children dealt with the family's Nazi past differently.
When Niklas wrote a book about his father in 1987 entitled "The Father: A Reckoning",
One of his brothers accused him of lying. On the other hand, Hans Frank's daughter, Sigfried,
moved to South Africa because he was in favor of apartheid. For her part, Brigitte,
The other sister suffered from cancer and committed suicide at the age of 46. The reason
to do so was that he did not want to live longer than his father, who was hanged at the same age.
No tears were shed for Hans Frank.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to give me a thumbs up
like to subscribe and click on the notification bell to
Don't miss our next videos thanks See you next time on the
canal